Guide to the Carl Gustav Hempel Papers, 1903-1997 ASP.1999.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Correspondence, 1924-1997; II.
  - General Correspondence, 1930-1996; 1.
    - Sakamoto, Hyakudai, 1970-1975 (Box 34, Folder 10)
    - Salmon, Wesley and Merrilee, 1962-1993 (Box 34, Folder 11)
    - Sambursky, Shmuel—Sayre, Kenneth M., 1951-1993 (Box 34, Folder 12)
    - Scanlon, Lucy— Schalit, Gabriele H., 1972-1987 (Box 34, Folder 13)
    - Schedel Ruth and Hansgeorg (Hempel's Relatives), 1953-1985 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Scheele, Raymond L. (Brentwood Public Schools), 1963 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Scheffler, Israel, 1952-1983 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Scheibe, Erhard—Schmidl, Fritz, 1953-1983 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Schneewind, Jerome—Schoenmun, R.B., 1955-1972 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Scholem, Gershorn—Schuster, Cynthia, 1969-1982 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Schuyler, William—Schwartz, Robert, 1962-1978 (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - Science (American Assoc. for the Advancement of Science), 1965-1967 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Scott, Dana—Scriven, Michael, 1955-1980 (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - Seattle University, 1982 (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - Seidenfeld, Teddy—Sen, Pranab Kumar, 1967-1980 (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - Villa, Serbelloni (see: Rockefeller Foundation) (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - Shapere, Dudley—Sheffer, Henry M., 1939-1991 (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - Shehadi, Fadlou—Siegwart, George, 1954-1991 (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - Sijthoff's, A.W., Uitgeurersmaatschappis N.V., 1936-1963 (Box 36, Folder 11)
    - Simili, Raffaella—Smart, J.J.C., 1951-1982 (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - Smith, James Ward—Smith, Vincent E., 1950-1980 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Smokler, Howard—Sobel, Howard, 1964-1981 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Social Science Research Council, 1963 (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - Sociedad Española de Lógica y Filosofía de la Ciencia (Carlos Solís), 1996 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - Solomon, Robert—Soto, Carlos, H., 1956-1979 (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Soviet Jews, 1964 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Spiegelberg, Herbert: see folder CH 39-04 "Washington University" (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Spohn, Wolfgang—Sprout, Harold, 1965-1992 (Box 37, Folder 8)
    - St. Andrews, University of (includes photos), 1986-1987 (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - St. John's University, 1971 (Box 37, Folder 10)
    - Stace, Walter—Stadler, Friedrich, 1956-1992 (Box 37, Folder 11)
    - Stegmüller, Margret and Wolfgang: Mostly Documents re. Death & Succession, 1981-1992 (Box 37, Folder 12)
    - Stegmüller, Wolfgang, 1977-1992 (Box 37, Folder 13)
    - Stegmüller, Wolfgang, 1958-1977 (Box 37, Folder 14)
    - Stein, Howard—Stemmar, Nathan, 1972-1980 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Stern, Dr. Raphael (Institute for Philosophy of Science: Psychotherapy and Ethics) (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Sternfeld, Robert—Ströbel, Hermann, 1942-1979 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Suhrkamp, Verlag, 1977 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Suppe, Fred, 1969-1984 (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Suppes, Patrick—Swartz, Norman, 1971-1992 (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - Synthese, 1964-1980 (Box 38, Folder 7)
    - Syracuse University, 1974-1977 (Box 38, Folder 8)
    - Szathmary, Arthur—Taylor, Richard, 1940-1983 (Box 38, Folder 9)
    - Technology Reviews, undated (Box 38, Folder 10)
    - Tel Aviv (separate folders for: Elkana and Margalit other correspondence), 1982-1984 (Box 38, Folder 11)
    - Theory and Decision, 1969 (Box 38, Folder 12)
    - Thiel, Christian—Thorn, Richard, 1978-1991 (Box 38, Folder 13)
    - Thost, Hanna Carnap, 1971-1973 (Box 38, Folder 14)
    - Tooley, Michael, 1972-1974 (Box 38, Folder 15)
    - Tondl, Ladislav—Trapp, Rainer, 1954-1987 (Box 38, Folder 16)
    - Trent University, 1973 (Box 38, Folder 17)
    - Trout, J.D.—Uebel, Thomas, 1956-1992 (Box 38, Folder 18)
    - University of Adelaide, 1978-1981 (Box 38, Folder 19)
    - University of Amsterdam, 1969-1973 (Box 38, Folder 20)
    - University of California at Berkeley: Visiting Professor, Spring, 1977, 1976-1977 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - University of California at Berkeley: Visiting Professor, Winter 1975 (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - University of California, Irvine: Visiting Professor May, 1978 (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - University of California, Los Angeles, 1971 and 1977 (Box 39, Folder 4)
    - University of California Press, 1961-1970 (Box 39, Folder 5)
    - University Center at Binghamton (N.Y.) re. Jerrold Arouson, 1984 (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - University of Chicago—HPS Panel, 1967-1968 (Box 39, Folder 7)
    - University of Chicago Press (Includes Royalty Reports), 1945-1982 (Box 39, Folder 8)
    - University College London, 1971-1972 (Box 39, Folder 9)
    - University of Colorado at Boulder, 1976 and 1977 (Box 39, Folder 10)
    - University of Delhi, 1972 (Box 39, Folder 11)
    - University of Hawaii, 1968 (Box 39, Folder 12)
    - University of Houston, 1966 (Box 39, Folder 13)
    - University of Ibadan (Nigeria) (Box 39, Folder 14)
    - University of Iowa, 1981 (Box 39, Folder 15)
    - University of Kansas, 1963 (Box 39, Folder 16)
    - University of Mexico, 1974-1977 (Box 39, Folder 17)
    - University of Miami, 1966-1970 (Box 39, Folder 18)
    - University of Michigan, 1978 and 1980 (Box 39, Folder 19)
    - University of Minnesota, 1955-1981 (Box 39, Folder 20)
    - University of Missouri, 1973 (Box 39, Folder 21)
    - University of North Carolina, 1964 and 1978 (Box 39, Folder 22)
    - University of Ottawa, 1978 and 1979 (Box 39, Folder 23)
    - University of Pennsylvania, 1972-1979 (Box 39, Folder 24)
    - University of Pittsburgh, Archives of Scientific Philosophy, 1985-1991 (Box 39, Folder 25)
    - University of Pittsburgh—Carnap Committee, 1974-1975 (Box 39, Folder 26)
    - University of Pittsburgh Correspondence, Covering Appointment and Time Here, 1975-1984 (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - University of Pittsburgh—Lecture Series (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - University of Pittsburgh—Philosophy Dept., 1980 and 1981 (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - University of Pittsburgh Press (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - University of Puerto Rico, 1954-1957 (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - University of Puget Sound, 1984 (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - Université du Québec a Montréal (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - University of Richmond, 1984 (Box 40, Folder 8)
    - University of South Carolina, 1958 (Box 40, Folder 9)
    - University of Southern California, 1978 and 1979 (Box 40, Folder 10)
    - University of Sydney (Box 40, Folder 11)
    - University of Vermont, 1978-1979 (Box 40, Folder 12)
    - University of Virginia, 1972 (Box 40, Folder 13)
    - University of Washington, 1952-1959 (Box 40, Folder 14)
    - University of Western Australia, 1978-1979 (Box 40, Folder 15)
    - University of Wisconsin, 1977-1979 (Box 40, Folder 16)
    - Unseld, van Nuis Pieter, 1950-1987 (Box 40, Folder 17)
    - Vassar College, 1950-1971 (Box 40, Folder 18)
    - Veltrusky, Jiŕi—Vetter, Hermann, 1948-1966 (Box 40, Folder 19)
    - Victoria and Albert Museum, undated (Box 40, Folder 20)
    - Vienna, Wiener Festwochen: Ring-Vorlesung "Das geistige Leben Wiens in der Zwischenkriegszeit", 1980 (Box 40, Folder 21)
    - Visva-Bharati University, 1969 (Box 40, Folder 22)
    - Vjecsner, Paul, 1992 (Box 40, Folder 23)
    - Vlastos, Gregory (Part I), 1955-1964 (Box 40, Folder 24)
    - Vlastos, Gregory (Part II), 1966-1989 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Vlastos, Gregory Memorial, 1991 and 1992 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Vlastos, Kimou K.—Wallace, John R., 1955-1992 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Wang, Jün-Tin—Watkins, John, 1952-1992 (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - Weaver, Warren—Weinberger, Rudolph, R., 1950-1989 (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - Weiss, Paul—Werkmeister, W.H., 1963-1969 (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - Wesleyan University, 1978 (Box 41, Folder 7)
    - Wesleyan University Press, 1963 and 1964 (Box 41, Folder 8)
    - Wessel, Horst, 1984-1986 (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - Western Reserve University, 1964 (Box 41, Folder 10)
    - Wheeler, John A.—Wigner, Eugene P., 1952-1990 (Box 41, Folder 11)
    - Westdeutsche Rektorenkonferenz, 1981-1982 (Box 41, Folder 12)
    - Wiley, John and Sons Inc., Publishers, 1963-1964 (Box 41, Folder 13)
    - Wilkins, Burleigh, 1963-1980 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Will, Frederick L., 1968-1978 (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Willer, Jörg—Wilson, Thomas J., 1948-1983 (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - Wimsatt, William C.—Wiseman, Ruthie, 1955-1983 (Box 42, Folder 4)
    - Wissenschaftskolleg zu Berlin: List of Fellows, Diverse Communications, 1981-1985 (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - Wissenschaftskolleg zu Berlin: Correspondence, Prospectuses, Abrechnungen, DAAD Material, 1982-1984 (Box 42, Folder 6)
    - Wissenschaftskolleg zu Berlin: Correspondence re. Fellow Club, "Self-Report," and Payment Pfaus, 1983-1991 (Box 42, Folder 7)
    - Witten, Edward—Wohlwill, Joachim and Faye, 1966-1986 (Box 42, Folder 8)
    - Wójcicki, Ryszard, 1965-1976 (Box 42, Folder 9)
    - Wojdyga, Krzysztof—Wolters, Gereon, 1968-1991 (Box 42, Folder 10)
    - Wood, Ledger, 1959-1963 (Box 42, Folder 11)
    - Woodger, J. H. (Socrates), 1952-1954 (Box 42, Folder 12)
    - Woodrow Wilson Foundation, 1964 (Box 42, Folder 13)
    - Woodruff, Arthur E. (Kim) (Box 42, Folder 14)
    - World Law, Grenville Clark Institute for, 1965-1967 (Box 42, Folder 15)
    - World Politics, 1968 (Box 42, Folder 16)
    - Worob, Avraham—Worrall, John, 1972 and 1984 (Box 42, Folder 17)
    - Worth Publishers (Walter L. Meagher), 1966 (Box 42, Folder 18)
    - Wort Verwertungsgesellschaft, 1983-1988 (Box 42, Folder 19)
    - Yale University and University Press, 1971-1982 (Box 43, Folder 1)
    - Yamasaki, Beatrice T.—Yevick, Miriam L., 1968-1992 (Box 43, Folder 2)
    - York University, Toronto: Canadian Invitation, 1968-1970 (Box 43, Folder 3)
    - Yoseido Gallery, Tokyo, 1964 (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - Yoshida, Keriji—Young, Kimball, 1950-1983 (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Yourgrau, Wolfgang, 1959-1968 [CLOSED] (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Zabludowski, Andrzej—Zen, M. T. (Bandung), 1963-1973 (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Zetetic Scholar, 1980 (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - Zharn, Peter Joseph—Zuesse, Eric, 1951-1982 (Box 43, Folder 9)
    - Overdue Correspondence, A-W, 1973-1975 (Box 43, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence between Paul Oppenheim, Kurt Grelling, and C.G. Hempel and Related Material, 1930-1974; 2.
    The Oppenheim-Hempel-Grelling correspondence testifies to Hempel's and Paul Oppenheim's ultimately failing efforts to help Kurt Grelling and his family to immigrate to the U.S. during their internment in camps in southern France under the Vichy regime during 1940-1942. Grelling and his wife died in 1942, probably at the concentration camp of Auschwitz or Birkenau.
    - Correspondence between Hempel and Paul Oppenheim re. Emigration Efforts for Kurt Grelling and His Family, 1936-1946 (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence between Kurt Grelling, Paul Oppenheim, and Hempel re. Emigration Efforts for Kurt Grelling and His Family, 1939-1942 (Box 44, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence by Oppenheim With Various Individuals (apparently from Oppenheim Papers) re. Emigration Efforts for Kurt Grelling and His Family, 1940-1941 (Box 44, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence by Oppenheim With Various Individuals (apparently from Oppenheim Papers) re. Emigration Efforts for Kurt Grelling and His Family, 1941-1944 (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - Reprints, Preprints, and Manuscripts by Grelling and by Both Grelling and Oppenheim, 1930-1949 and undated (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Reprints, Preprints, and Manuscripts by Grelling and by Both Grelling and Oppenheim, 1938-1939, 1961 (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence between Oppenheim and Edith and Abraham Luchins re. Kurt Grelling, 1964-1974 (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and Discussions Notes between Hempel, Oppenheim, and Other Correspondents (Rudolf Carnap, Olaf Helmer, Felix Oppenheim, and John Kemeny), 1944-1992; 3.
    - Correspondence between Oppenheim, Helmer, and Carnap: Exchange on Probability Issues (Terminology, Decision Problems, etc.), 1944-1945 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence Hempel-Oppenheim, 1951-1992 (Box 45, Folder 2-6)
    - Correspondence with and regarding Felix Oppenheim, 1957-1984 (Box 45, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence Oppenheim-John Kemeny, 1955-1959 (Box 45, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence Oppenheim-John Kemeny, 1947-1954 (Box 45, Folder 9)
  - Family Correspondence with Hempel's Relatives and Ahrends Family [Restricted], 1954-1991; 4.
    The family correspondence covers mainly exchanges between Hempel and members of his family in then East and West Germany, and with relatives of his former wife Eva Hempel, née Ahrends. Featured is correspondence with his brother Heinz Hempel, his nephews Ulrich, Jürg, and Klaus Hempel; and with his sister-in-law Lux Lessel, Eva Hempel's sister, and Edmund Ahrends, Eva Hempel's father.
    - Lessel, Lux (née Ahrends), 1954-1965 (Box 46, Folder 1)
    - Lessel, Lux (née Ahrends), 1966-1993 (Box 46, Folder 2)
    - Ahrends, Edmund (Father-in-Law), 1950-1965 (Box 46, Folder 3)
    - Hempel, Heinz (Brother) and Ulrich, Jürg, and Klaus Hempel (Nephews), 1968-1983 (Box 46, Folder 4)
    - Hempel, Jürg and Ulrich (Nephews), 1985-1991 (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - Letters of Recommendation [CLOSED], 1941-1985; 5.
    Please note that this series is currently closed and not open to research use due to the personal and confidential nature of the material.
    - Recommendations Non-Students A-W, 1941-1974 (Box 47, Folder 1-3)
      Scope and Contents
    - Recommendations Students A-Z, 1941-1966 (Box 47, Folder 4-5)
    - Recommendations Princeton Undergraduates, 1953-1974 (Box 47, Folder 6-7)
    - Recommendations Princeton A-S, 1955-1985 (Box 48, Folder 1-7)
    - Recommendations Princeton T-W, 1956-1967 (Box 49, Folder 1)
    - Recommendations Yale A-Y, 1949-1966 (Box 49, Folder 2-4)
- Research, Lectures, and Publications, 1918-1992; III.
  This series comprises records on Hempel's academic and scholarly activities. The material is divided into seven subseries that reflect major areas of his core intellectual involvement and research. Subseries 1focuses on general research material, such as notes, reading and reference material, and clippings of articles. Subseries 2 concentrates on manuscripts and drafts for publication. Subseries 3 centers around general lecture notes, whereas subseries 4 and 5 focus specifically on the Carus and the Gavin David Young lectures. Subseries 6 comprises writings by others in form of drafts, typescripts, and reprints; subseries 7 contains inserts and notes found in Hempel's books and Hempel's index cards; and subseries 8 features early reviews by C. G. Hempel and Eva Ahrends-Hempel.
  - General Research Material, 1918-1972; 1.
    - Reprints and Typescripts by Others on 3D-Space, and Axiomatization of Scientific Theories: Bunge, Carnap, Resnik, Wightman et. al, 1918-1970 (Box 50, Folder 1)
    - Reprints by Hempel and Others on Induction and Confirmation, 1945-1969 (Box 50, Folder 2-4)
    - Reprints and Galleys by Hempel: "Scientific Explanation" (Voice of America Broadcast)"Some Remarks on 'Facts' and Propositions" and "On the Structures of Scientific Theories", 1969 (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - Quine Ad: Hangman's Paradox, Notes by Hempel, 1946 (Box 50, Folder 6)
    - Topics to Think About and Reading Lists, 1966-1972 (Box 50, Folder 7)
    - Articles Ad Philosophy of Science from Scientific American, New York Times, et al., 1973-1982 (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - On Einstein: Material on Albert Einstein (in German), 1979 (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - University of Chicago: Workshop in Economic History, Schedule and List of Papers Presented at Previous Workshops, 1971-1972 (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Material Borrowed by Jeffrey and Returned July 9, 1998, 1937-1998 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - 2022 Addition, c. 1940-1961
      - Bibliographic Index Cards, 1940-1961 (Box 93)
        One file card box contains entries for books and book chapters; a second contains entries for reprints of journal articles. Cf. Series VI, Offprints.
      - Transcripts of interviews: 17 March 1982; 24 March 1982; 1 August 1983, 1982-1983 (Box 51, Folder 5)
  - Manuscripts for Publication, 1953-1994; 2.
    - Philosophical Essays, Early and Late (1934-1937), 1994 (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - "The Problem of Truth" (1937), 1994 (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - "Limits of Science": Reprints, Photocopies, and Excerpts of Relevant Literature (Part I), undated (Box 52, Folder 3)
    - "Limits of Science": Reprints, Photocopies, and Excerpts of Relevant Literature, including Du Bois-Reymond & Tyndall (Part II), 1968 (Box 52, Folder 4)
    - "Limits of Science": Reprints, Photocopies, and Excerpts of Relevant Literature, including Du Bois-Reymond & Tyndall (Part III), 1968 (Box 52, Folder 5)
    - 2nd Edition of Philosophy of Natural Science: Additional Material, 1953-1973 and undated (Box 52, Folder 6)
    - Corrigenda for Hempel's Aspects of Scientific Explanation, 1965 (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - Aspects of Scientific Explanation, Revision Notes (Part I), 1968-1970 (Box 52, Folder 8)
    - Aspects of Scientific Explanation, Revision Notes (Part II), 1967-1970 (Box 53, Folder 1)
    - Ad Limits: Duplicate Notes, July 1971, 1965-1969 (Box 53, Folder 2)
    - Ad Limits: Notes & Literature (no lecture mss.), 1968-1969 (Box 53, Folder 3)
    - "In Memory of Rudolf Carnap," Obituary by C.G. Hempel, 1970 (Box 53, Folder 4)
    - "Theoretical Concepts and Theory Change: A Postscript," Text of Chapter IV of German Edition of Fundamentals of Concept Formation in Empirical Science. (Finished February 1974) (Box 53, Folder 5)
    - "Theoretical Concepts and Theory Change: A Postcript," (shorter version of typed text), 1974 (Box 53, Folder 6)
    - "Postcript 1976: More Recent Ideas on the Problem of Statistical Explanation," Originally Published in the German Translation of Hempel's Aspects of Scientific Explanation (Box 53, Folder 7)
    - "Vorwort zur Deutschen Ausgabe von Aspekte wissenschaftlichen Erklärens," and "Nachwort 1976: Neuere Ideen zu den Problemen der statistischen Erklärung," 1976 (Box 53, Folder 8)
    - "Schlick und Neurath: Fundierung vs. Kohärenz in der wissenschaftlichen Erkenntnis", 1982-1983 (Box 53, Folder 9)
    - "Provisoes: A Problem Concerning the Inferential Function of Scientific Theories", 1985 (Box 53, Folder 10)
    - "Eino Kaila and Logical Empiricism," Proofs of Lecture at the Kaila Symposium Helsinki, October 1990, for publication in Acta Philosophica Fennica 52, and correspondence with Ilkka Niiniluoto, 1990-1991 (Box 53, Folder 11)
    - "The Vienna Circle and the Metamorphosis of Its Empiricism", undated (Box 53, Folder 12)
    - "Schlick and Neurath: Foundation vs. Coherence in Scientific Knowledge", undated (Box 53, Folder 13)
    - "Notes re. Probability", undated (Box 53, Folder 14)
  - General Lecture Notes, 1935-1992; 3.
    Hempel's writings and recollections about the Vienna Circle are part of this subseries, compiled in five folders titled "Empiricism Berlin and Vienna." Hempel apparently gathered this material in preparation for various lectures and talks on the Vienna Circle. However, no original documents from the Berlin Circle are included here. The only items of that period are letters to Albrecht Becker-Freyseng reporting about his studies and impressions of the Vienna Circle while studying in Vienna during the winter semester of 1929-1930 and comparing the Berlin and Viennese academic environments. Additional correspondence with Albrecht Becker-Freyseng can be found in the correspondence series.
    - "Scientific Philosophy": WIND Radio Talk, Chicago, 1939 (Box 54, Folder 1)
    - "The Legacy of Logical Positivism for the Philosophy of Science," Johns Hopkins University; Literature on Behaviorism, Neurath, Philosophy of Social Sciences, 1965-1967 (Box 54, Folder 2)
    - "On Thearetical Terms and Theoretical Entities," NY Philosophy Club, 1966, and 1967 Seminar Notes on the Existence of Theoretical Entities, 1966-1967 (Box 54, Folder 3)
    - "On the Limits of Scientific Understanding," American Philosophical Society, 1967 (Box 54, Folder 4)
    - "On the Limits of Scientific Understanding" (Xerox Copy), Hawaii, 1968 (Box 54, Folder 5)
    - "On the Limits of Scientific Understanding," Hawaii Paper, Comments by D. Kaplan, 1968-1969 (Box 54, Folder 6)
    - "The Problem of Application: The Logic of Theoretical Inference" and "Limitations of Deductionism," 1970-1980. (Box 54, Folder 7)
    - "Science Unlimited?" Matchette Lecture, Purdue, 1971 (Box 54, Folder 8)
    - "Science Unlimited?" Machette Lecture, 1971 and Some Addenda., 1971-1976 (Box 54, Folder 9)
    - "Are there Limits to Scientific Understanding?": Text, Lecture List, Notes, Addenda, Reprints, 1973-1980 (Box 54, Folder 10)
    - "Analytic Empiricist Perspectives on Science in the Light of Recent Criticism," & Notes, 1973-1975 (Box 54, Folder 11)
    - "Modes & Scopes of Scientific Understanding": Important Addenda & Supplements, incl. v. Wright; Empathy & Higham Quote, 1973-1977 (Box 54, Folder 12)
    - "Deskriptive & Normative Aspekte der Wissenschaftstheorie," Ms. Bielefeld Lecture, 1975 (Box 55, Folder 1)
    - "Die Wissenschaftstheorie des analytischen Empirismus im Lichte zeitgenössischer Kritik," Philosophy Congress Göttingen, 1975-1976 (Box 55, Folder 2)
    - "Die Wissenschaftstheorie des analytischen Empirismus im Lichte zeitgenössischer Kritik," Philosophy Congress Göttingen, 1975-1976 (Box 55, Folder 3)
    - Notes by Hempel and Others on Rationality, Rational Reconstruction, Analytic vs. Pragmatist Approaches, 1975-1978 (Box 55, Folder 4)
    - "Reflections on the Exploration of Actions," Northfield Noumenal Society, Carleton College, 1976 (Box 55, Folder 5)
    - "Are there Limits to Scientific Understanding?" Lecture at Carleton College and University of Pittsburgh, 1976 (Box 55, Folder 6)
    - Hempel's Notes on "FATE" Discussion, University of Pittsburgh & Carnegie Mellon University Undergraduate Philosophy Club, 1976 (Box 55, Folder 7)
    - "Certainty," Lecture Hameline University, 1976 (Box 55, Folder 8)
    - "Scientific Rationality & Rational Reconstruction," & Related Correspondence, Chapel Hill Colloquium, 1976 (Box 55, Folder 9)
    - Notes on Science & Rationality; Explication, 1976 and Undated (Box 55, Folder 10)
    - "Science & Rationality," Undated (Box 55, Folder 11)
    - "Scientific Rationality: Analytic vs. Pragmatic Perspectives," Ottawa '77 Paper, 1977-1978 (Box 55, Folder 12)
    - Mexico: 2nd National Conference of Philosophy, Monterrey: Papers by Hempel & Others, & Correspondence, 1977 (Box 55, Folder 13)
    - Workshop on Logic of Discovery and Diagnosis in Medicine October. 6, 7, 8, 1978. Hempel's Comments and Notes, Related Correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box 56, Folder 1)
    - "Science and Pseudo-Science," Notes for Talk in Ezra T. Olewmans Course of Same Title, 1978 (Box 56, Folder 2)
    - "Scientific Rationality: Normative vs. Description Construals," John Dewey Lecture, University of Vermont, 1978 (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - "Scientific Rationality: Normative vs. Description Construals," Oaxaca – John Dewey Lecture, October 1978 (Box 56, Folder 4)
    - "Science & Rationality" and "Scientific Rationality" (revised), Kirchberg Lecture, 1978-1979 (Box 56, Folder 5)
    - "Modes & Scope of Scientific Understanding," Wesleyan University, 1978-1979 (Box 56, Folder 6)
    - "Notes on Rationality of Science" "Explication" "Epistemology Naturalized", 1978-1982 (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - "Der Wiener Kreis: Eine persönliche Perspektive," Kirchberg Lecture, 1979 (Box 56, Folder 8)
    - "On Explaining Human Behavior" University of Pittsburgh Colloquium, 1979 (Box 56, Folder 9)
    - "Old & New Riddles of Induction," University of Pittsburgh & Carnegie Mellon Undergraduate Philosophy Club, 1979 (Box 56, Folder 10)
    - "On Explaining Human Behavior," Symposium Paper University of Pittsburgh, 1979 (Box 56, Folder 11)